A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Program Division, Office of the Vice President, Office Files of James H. Lapple FA599
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Program Division, Office of the Vice President, Office Files of James H. Lapple
1971-1997
Rockefeller Archive Center
Lapple, James H.
Ford Foundation
FA599
12.97 Cubic Feet 33 containers
Immediate Source of Acquisition
James Lapple's material arrived at the RAC in six accessions between 2011 and 2019 (Accessions 2011:072 [Boxes 48116-48118], 2012:040 [Boxes 48662-48665], 2012:056 [48619-48622], 2018:066 [Box 39023], 2019:102 [Box 40187], and 2019:152 [Boxes 43305-43306, 43524])
Accession 2011:072 was processed as FA599 in September 2011 by Rachel Moskowitz, The Winthrop Group. The original volume of 3 cubic feet accessioned in 2011 was reduced during processing to 1.6 cubic feet and transferred to 4 archival document boxes. Duplicates, reference files and background materials, grant proposals, and files that addressed purely financial matters were not retained.
In October 2018, Accession 2018:066 was added to FA599 as Series 4: Management Files, 1991-1992.
Accession 2012:040 was minimally processed as FA661 in December 2013.
Accession 2012:056 was minimally processed as FA683 in December 2013.
In 2020 and 2021, all accessions and collections were consolidated into FA599.
Accessions 2019:102 and 2019:152 were processed into FA599 in June 2021.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Scope and Contents
The Office Files of James H. Lapple span from 1971 to 1997. The collection documents his work as Manager of Operations and Grant Administration within the Office of the Vice President of the Program Division. Mr. Lapple monitored the activities of and decisions made by Foundation staff abroad. Program reviews and field office reports make up the bulk of the collection and detail the activities and operations of Foundation staff and grant recipients. Budget projections and expenditure reports describe in detail the funding allotted for each program and, within each, how and where money was distributed and spent. The meeting documents reveal the objectives of the Program Division and how funding was appropriated, allocated, and used to support activities. They illustrate accounting and grant-making processes, information and records management systems, and employment and hiring policies, and highlight their changing nature as the Foundation sought more efficient modes of operation. In addition, Mr. Lapple's papers reveal his involvement in the establishment of field offices, including the engagement of local attorneys hired to secure the legal documentation necessary for the Foundation to operate overseas, and the search for and lease of office space. The records also illustrate employee lodging and subsequent property renovations and employment issues regarding Foundation consultants and local staff members.
Of particular note are the files revealing field office practices for administering grant funding to local recipients. Prior to the late 1980s and early 1990s, each regional office developed its own system for monitoring and distributing grant funding. Mr. Lapple proved instrumental in standardizing the process by implementing a computer-generated field office grants system (FOGS) and arranging for the installation of the corresponding software in regional offices.
Biographical Note
James H. Lapple graduated from St. Bonaventure University in 1984 with a Bachelor's in Business Administration and a focus on Accounting. He later earned both an MBA and a CPA. From 1984 to 1986, Mr. Lapple worked as a staff accountant for Price Waterhouse and, in April 1986, joined the Ford Foundation as a senior accountant for International Operations within the Office of the Secretary, Legal, Financial and Administrative Services. In January 1990, Mr. Lapple became the Manager of Operations within the Office of the Vice President of the Program Division. He was promoted in April 1994 to the role of Manager of Operations and Grants Administration for the entire Program Division. In these roles, Mr. Lapple oversaw the finances and accounting practices of the international field offices, monitored grant-making budgets, and supervised and supported field office employees. He traveled often and supported and assisted with field office operations both from the New York headquarters and on his many trips. Mr. Lapple resigned in August 1997 to work for the Institute of International Education where he served as Vice President for Finance and Administration. In 2004, he became the Treasurer of Rockefeller University. Currently Mr. Lapple is the Vice President for Finance and the Associate Treasurer at Rockefeller University.
Organizational Note
The Program Division was created in 1989 to streamline the supervision of the Ford Foundation's worldwide programming initiatives. The division's main department, the Office of the Vice President, absorbed the responsibilities of two previously independent programs: the United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) and the Developing Countries Program (DCP).
The Developing Countries Program consisted of three regions: Latin America and the Caribbean (LAC); Asia and the Pacific (ASIA); and Africa and the Middle East (AME). Each region was further subdivided into zones operated by a field office. The LAC region included three zones: a Brazil office, a Mexico office, and two offices within the Andean Region and the Southern Cone (a main office in Santiago, Chile which opened in 1991 and a sub-office in Lima, Peru). ASIA was divided into four zones with offices in India, Bangladesh, and China, and three offices in Southeast Asia (a main office in Indonesia, and two sub-offices in the Philippines and Thailand). AME was divided into three zones with a main and a sub-office in each zone. The North Africa and Middle East zone included a main office in Egypt and a sub-office in the Sudan; West Africa consisted of a main office in Senegal and a sub-office in Nigeria; and Eastern and Southern Africa activities operated out of a main office in Kenya and a sub-office in Zimbabwe.
Both main and sub-offices oversaw the implementation of initiatives and worked together to coordinate programming and grantee activity. The representative of each zone and the bulk of the program staff worked out of the main office. In geographically broad zones, an assistant representative often worked out in a sub-office. This practice expanded the Foundation's presence and ensured that even large regions would have adequately coverage by Foundation staff. Depending on shifting interests and social, political, and economic conditions within the regions, field offices periodically relocated from one country to another. The Andean Region and the Southern Cone experienced this when, in the early 1990s, the Foundation decided to convert its Lima office into a sub-office and establish a new main office in Santiago, Chile.
The United States and International Affairs Program also consisted of several divisions. By the early 1990s, these programs included Education and Culture; International Affairs; Rights and Social Justice; Governance and Public Policy; Program-Related Investments; Reproductive Health and Population; Rural Poverty and Resources; Urban Poverty; and the Office of the Vice President. With the Foundation's reorganization of 1997 and the termination of a distinct department designed to supervise worldwide programming, the responsibilities once delegated to the Program Division transferred to three new program areas: Asset Building and Community Development (ASSETS); Education, Media, Arts and Culture (EMAC); and Peace and Social Justice (PSJ).
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two series:
1.) Program Reviews and Budgets, 1987-1994
2.) Field Office Files, 1971-1997
The collection is comprised of boxes that came to the RAC over a period of 9 years. The material has been arranged broadly by topic "as received." Some material, primarily budget files, are arranged chronologically and some field office material is arranged alphabetically by program area or field office location.
Ford Foundation organization -- Field offices; Program budgeting
- Program Reviews and Budgets, 1987-1994; 1; 5.39 Cubic Feet 13 containers
  Biographical / Historical
  The Program Division was created in 1989 to streamline the supervision of the Ford Foundation's worldwide programming initiatives. The division's main department, the Office of the Vice President, absorbed the responsibilities of two previously independent programs: the United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) and the Developing Countries Program (DCP).
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains field office budget and expenditure reports as well as related interoffice memoranda with background and additional information about the finances and accounting of Ford field offices.
  The program review meeting files consist of agendas, budget projections, interoffice memoranda, handwritten notes and additional materials. The Program Division held meetings each year, including mid-year and six-month budget reviews, DCP/USIAP joint program reviews, and individual review sessions for DCP and USIAP divisions. During these meetings, program officers and directors reported on expenditures, existing and future programming, and grant distribution and shared budget projections. The files also hold reports and papers detailing work accomplished within the programs.
  Of particular note is the Field Office Delegation of Authority manual, found with the 1991 Joint Program Review materials. It details the responsibilities and functions of field office staff and regional representatives. It delineates the duties of field office representatives, assistant representatives, and program officers and paints a more vivid picture of the management of Foundation offices abroad.
  - United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) - Governance and Public Policy (GPP) - Budget Projections, 1989 February (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Developing Countries Program(DCP)/ United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) - Memoranda Re: New Budget Reports, 1989 August-September (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Developing Countries Program(DCP)/ United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) Program Review (April 1990) -- Agendas, Memoranda, Status Reports, Handwritten Notes, 1990 January-June (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) - Human Rights and Social Justice (HRJ) - Budget Projections, 1990 March (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) - Program-Related Investments (PRI) - Budget Projections, 1990 June (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) - Governance and Public Policy - Budget Projections, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Developing Countries Program(DCP)/United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) Mid-Year Budget Review (March 1991) - Agendas, Memoranda, Budget and Expenditures Reports, 1991 March (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Developing Countries Program(DCP)/United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) Joint Program Review (April-May 1991) -Agendas, Memoranda, Meeting Materials, Notes from Sessions, 1991 January-May (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Developing Countries Program(DCP)/United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) Joint Program Review - Budget Session (5/6/91) - Agenda, Memoranda, Meeting Materials, 1991 April-June (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Developing Countries Program(DCP)/United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) Joint Program Review - Regional Sub-office Luncheon/Meeting (5/6/91) - Agenda, Meeting Materials Re: Sub-Office Issues and Grant Administration, 1991 May (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Developing Countries Program(DCP)/United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) Joint Program Review - Field Office Delegation of Authority Manual, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Developing Countries Program(DCP)/United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) - Budget Reports, Memoranda and Handwritten Notes Re: Fiscal Year 1991 and 1992 Expenditures and Staff, 1991 March-August (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) Program Review - Session Agendas for Jan-Feb 1992 Meetings, 1991 December (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) Program Review - Governance and Public Policy (1/9/92) - Agenda, Memoranda, Budget Projections, 1992 January (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) Program Review - Urban Poverty (1/10/92) - Memoranda and Budget Projections, 1991 October-1992 January (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) Program Review - Program-Related Investments (1/14/92) - Agenda and Grant Projections, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) Program Review - International Affairs (2/5/92) - Agenda, Memoranda, Budget Projections, 1992 January (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) Program Review - Education and Culture (2/6/92) - Agenda, Memoranda, Budget Projections, 1992 January-February (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) Program Review - Rights and Social Justice (2/7/92) - Agenda, Memoranda, Meeting Materials, Budget Projections, 1991 December-1992 February (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Contains Report 013576
  - United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) Program Review - Reproductive Health and Population (2/14/92) - Agenda, Memoranda, Budget Projections, 1992 January-February (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) Program Review - Rural Poverty and Resources (2/14/92) - Agenda, Memoranda, Budget Projections, Worldwide Funds, 1992 January-February (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Developing Countries Program(DCP)/United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) 6-Month Budget Review (March 1992) - Program Budget Reports, 1992 March-May (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Developing Countries Program(DCP)/United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) Joint Program Review (May 1992) - Agendas, Memoranda, Meeting Materials, 1992 January-May (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Developing Countries Program(DCP)/United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) Joint Program Review (May 1992) - Field Office Retention Guidelines (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) Program Review - Rights and Social Justice (3/4/93) - Agenda, Memoranda, Reports, Budget Projections, 1993 February-March (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Contains Reports 013577, 012714, 012418
  - United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) Program Review - Governance and Public Policy (3/9/93) - Agenda, Memoranda, Meeting Materials, Budget Projections, 1993 March (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Contains Report 012801
  - United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) Program Support Budgets, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) Program Support Budgets - Ratios, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) Program Support Budgets - Followup Memos, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) Program Support Budgets - Analysis (4 folders), 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 30-33)
  - United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) Program Support Budgets - Developing Country Programs Salaries, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) Program Support Budgets - 1992 Budget Instructions (2 folders), 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 35-36)
  - United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) Program Support Budgets - Budget Presentation, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) Program Support Budgets - Budget Calendarization Worksheets, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) 1992 Program Support Budgets (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - FY 1992 Capital Projects (Box 4, Folder 40-42)
  - FY 1992 Capital Projects - Building Drawing (Folder 343)
  - FY 1992 Capital Projects - Chile, 1991-1992 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - May Administrative Meeting - Schedules, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - May Administrative Meeting - Budgets - Budget Discussion Agenda, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - May Administrative Meeting - Accounting Software Review, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - May Administrative Meeting - Field Office Grants System, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - May Administrative Meeting - Original Representatives Letter and Planning Memoranda, 1990-1991 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - May Administrative Meeting - Participants List, Dinner Attendees, 1991 May (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - May Administrative Meeting - Participants List, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - May Administrative Meeting - Meeting Costs, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - May Administrative Meeting - Ford Foundation Archives - Meeting Agenda, Retention Guidelines, Risk Management for Field Offices Summary, Information on Preparing and Controlling Files, etc., 1991 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - May Administrative Meeting - Miscellaneous Meeting Materials, 1990-1991 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - May Administrative Meeting - Agenda, Fiscal Report, Ford Office Grants System (FOGS) Information, 1991 May 15-23 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Southeast Asia Regional Meeting - Bangkok, 1992 June 11-12 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Fiscal Year 1993 Program Division 7 Month Budget Review - Office of the Vice President and Grant Administration, May 1993 (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Fiscal Year 1993 Program Division 7 Month Budget Review - Urban Poverty, 1993 May (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - Fiscal Year 1993 Program Division 7 Month Budget Review - Rights and Social Justice, 1993 May (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Fiscal Year 1993 Program Division 7 Month Budget Review - Government and Public Policy, 1993 May (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Fiscal Year 1993 Program Division 7 Month Budget Review - International Affairs Program, 1993 May (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - Fiscal Year 1993 Program Division 7 Month Budget Review - Education and Culture, 1993 May (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Fiscal Year 1993 Program Division 7 Month Budget Review - Rural Poverty and Research, 1993 May (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Fiscal Year 1993 Program Division 7 Month Budget Review - Reproductive Health and Population, 1993 May (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - Fiscal Year 1993 Program Division 7 Month Budget Review - Program Related Investments, 1993 May (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - Fiscal Year 1993 Program Division 7 Month Budget Review - Africa and the Middle East, 1993 May (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - Fiscal Year 1993 Program Division 7 Month Budget Review - Latin America, 1993 May (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - Fiscal Year 1993 Program Division 7 Month Budget Review - Asia, 1993 May (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - Fiscal Year 1993 Program Division 7 Month Budget Review - List of Errors and Handwritten Budget Notes, 1993 May (Box 5, Folder 68)
  - 1993 Regional Meeting - Audit Session, 1992-1993 (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - 1993 Program Review (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - 1993 United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) Program Review - Education and Culture Program Review, 1993 February 9 (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - 1993 United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) Program Review - International Affairs Program Review, 1993 February 10 (Box 5, Folder 72)
  - 1993 United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) Program Reviews, 1993 January-February (Box 5, Folder 73)
  - 1993 United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) Program Reviews - Program Related Investments, Rural Poverty and Resources, Reproductive Health and Population, and Urban Poverty Program Reviews, 1993 January-February (Box 6, Folder 74)
  - United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) Program Review Fiscal Year 1994 - Rights and Social Justice, Governance and Public Policy, Reproductive Health and Population, 1993 November-December (Box 6, Folder 75-77)
    Tab 1: Program Review Agenda
    Tab 2: GPP Lines of Work
    Tab 3: Program Review Memoranda
    Tab 4: Exploration of Gun Violence
    Tab 5: GPP Budget
  - United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) Program Review Fiscal Year 1994 - Education and Culture, 1993 December 14 (Box 6, Folder 78)
  - United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) Program Review Fiscal Year 1994 - Media Projects Program Review, 1994 February 1 (Box 6, Folder 79)
  - Asia Regional Meeting (February 1994) - Meeting Preparation Materials, Administrative Procedures and Manuals for Field Offices, Field Office Inventory Lists, etc., 1988-1994 (Box 6, Folder 80-81, Box 7, Folder 82)
  - Inventory Backup for Delhi Meeting, 1994 September 2; 3.5" floppy disk (Box 6, Folder 80)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. Access copy currently unavailable. Please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
  - Manila, Philippines Inventory System Backup, undated; 5.25" floppy disk (Box 6, Folder 80)
  - Untitled Floppy Disk, undated; 3.5" floppy disk (Box 6, Folder 80)
  - Beijing Inventory System Backup, 1990 August 20; 3.5" floppy disk (Box 6, Folder 80)
  - United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) Budgets Fiscal Year 1991, 1990 August (Box 7, Folder 83)
  - United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) Fiscal Year 1992 Budgets Final (Box 7, Folder 84)
  - Fiscal Year 1992 Budgets - Developing Countries Program Ratios, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 85)
  - Fiscal Year 1992 Budgets - Presidents Review for Fiscal Year 1991, Includes Staff Count Analysis (Box 7, Folder 86)
  - Fiscal Year 1992 Budgets - United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) Ratios, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 87)
  - 1993 Budget Process, 1991-1993 (Box 7, Folder 88)
  - Fiscal Year 1993 Budget Summary - Ratios, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 89)
  - Fiscal Year 1993 Budget Summary - Budget Year End Follow-up, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 90-91)
  - Fiscal Year 1993 Budget Summary - Final 1992 Staff Count - Maddaline Kostyra Memorandum, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 92)
  - Fiscal Year 1993 Budget Summary - Calendarization, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 93)
  - Fiscal Year 1993 Budget Summary - Audit Checklist, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 94)
  - Fiscal Year 1993 Budget Summary - Staff Count Analysis, Field Office Capital Projects Requests, Funding Availability, 1992-1993 (Box 7, Folder 95)
  - Fiscal Year 1993 Budget Summary - Unit Reserve, 1992-1993 (Box 8, Folder 96-98)
  - April 1994 - Expense Analysis, Actual vs. Budgets, 1994 April (Box 8, Folder 99)
  - Financial Statements and Quarterly Projections, 1988-1990 (Box 8, Folder 100-101)
  - Monthly Financial Statements, 1989-1990 (Box 8, Folder 102)
  - Mexico Foundation Administered Project Visit/Review, 1989 August (Box 9, Folder 103)
  - January 1990 Budget Review (Box 9, Folder 104-106)
  - Cost Center Budget Reports - Regional Offices Fiscal Year 1990, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 107)
  - Roster and Staff Count, 1990 March (Box 9, Folder 109)